In the previous episode, I explored why
Articulate exists.
This time, I want to answer what should be
a
much simpler question.
What exactly is Articulate?
The problem is that the answer has changed
quite a few times.
At different points, Articulate has been a
documentation tool, a
knowledge graph, a conversational
assistant, a discovery platform and an
architecture modelling tool.
Each idea solved part of the problem.
But none of them really captured the
bigger picture.
Today, I see Articulate as an exploration
into something I
call architectural intelligence.
But to explain what I mean by that, I
first
need to talk about architectural
knowledge.
Most architecture tools are built around
artefacts.
We create documents, diagrams, decision
records and models.
All of those things are useful.
But each one only represents part of the
architecture.
The architecture itself is much more than
any individual artefact.
It includes facts and assumptions.
Evidence and decisions.
Capabilities, constraints and
relationships.
It includes why decisions were made, what
alternatives were considered
and how the architecture has changed over
time.
Together, all of this forms a body of
architectural knowledge.
And unlike a document, that knowledge
never really stops changing.
So one of the central ideas behind
Articulate is to
treat that architectural knowledge as the
primary asset.
Documents, diagrams and models still
exist.
But instead of being isolated sources of
information, they contribute
to a continuously evolving understanding
of the architecture.
This is where AI starts to become
interesting.
Articulate is designed from the outset as
an AI-native system.
But that does not mean replacing the
architect.
The architect still owns the decisions,
the judgement and ultimately the
accountability.
I see AI as a collaborator.
It can help discover information, identify
inconsistencies and challenge assumptions.
It can help explain relationships, reason
about change and surface
information that might otherwise be
difficult to find.
The objective isn't to automate
architecture.
It's to augment the architect.
And that leads to another important part
of Articulate.
Conversation.
Architects spend a lot of time asking
questions.
Why was this decision made?
What depends on this system?
What happens if we change this service?
Have we solved this problem somewhere else
before?
Today, answering those questions often
means searching through documents,
diagrams,
repositories and speaking to different
people.
If architectural knowledge can be
represented in a form that
AI can reason about, then conversation
becomes a natural way
of exploring it.
I should be able to ask Articulate a
question about
the architecture and have it gather the
relevant knowledge, understand
the relationships and help me reason about
the answer.
Conversation isn't the architecture.
And it isn't the knowledge model.
It's the interface through which I
collaborate with the system.
Behind that conversation is a continuously
evolving model of the architecture.
Discovery contributes knowledge.
Architecture decisions contribute
knowledge.
Solution designs contribute knowledge.
So do source code, infrastructure and
eventually operational information.
None of those sources necessarily tells us
the complete truth
on its own.
Instead, they provide evidence.
As new evidence becomes available, our
understanding of the architecture can
evolve.
That means the model is never really
finished.
And I think that's a much more realistic
representation of architecture.
Architecture isn't something we document
once and then periodically update.
It's something we are continuously
learning about.
This idea leads to a number of
capabilities that I
want to explore throughout the project.
Articulate needs to discover architectural
knowledge from different sources.
It needs to preserve that knowledge and
understand how it
changes over time.
It needs to let architects explore what is
known through
conversation and visualisation.
It should help us reason about the impact
of change.
It should support the solution design
process by challenging assumptions,
identifying constraints and preserving the
reasoning behind decisions.
And it should help us understand what
capabilities and solutions
already exist before we create something
new.
These aren't intended to be a fixed
feature list.
They are architectural capabilities that
will evolve as the project evolves.
And importantly, I don't yet know exactly
what all of
them will look like.
That's part of what this journal is here
to discover.
All of this brings me back to the phrase I
used at the beginning.
Architectural intelligence.
For me, architectural intelligence is the
ability to understand architecture,
preserve what we know about it, reason
about relationships and
decisions, and explore the consequences of
change.
That is the idea Articulate is ultimately
exploring.
Can we build systems that don't simply
store architecture documentation,
but actually help us reason about
architecture?
Can AI work alongside architects without
attempting to replace their judgement?
And can architectural knowledge become
something that continuously evolves rather
than something we periodically try to
document?
I don't know all of the answers yet.
And I expect some of the ideas behind
Articulate to
change considerably as I build it.
That's really the point of the project.
So, what is Articulate?
At this point in the journey, I would
describe it
as an exploration into architectural
intelligence.
An AI-native platform designed to help
architects understand, evolve and
reason about complex software systems.
The next step is to start turning that
ambition into an architecture.
And that means understanding the
principles, requirements and constraints
that
should shape the system before making
decisions about how to
build it.