Why does Articulate exist?
During my career as an architect,
I've come to appreciate that
architecture is rarely constrained by
technology alone. Most modern
technology is remarkably capable.
Cloud platforms can scale globally.
Frameworks are mature. Infrastructure
can be provisioned in minutes.
AI can generate code,
explain documentation and
automate many development tasks.
Yet, with all these advances,
one problem remains remarkably consistent.
Understanding the architecture itself.
Not the diagrams or the documentation,
but the architecture.
Regardless of the organisation,
industry or tech stack,
architects spend a significant
proportion of their time trying to answer
surprisingly simple questions, like:
What does the current
architecture look like?
Or why was it designed
like this? What changed?
Can we trust the documentation?
Who knows the answer?
These questions rarely have
straightforward answers.
This episode explores why I
believe that problem exists,
why existing tools only solve part of it,
and why I think recent advances in AI
make it worth exploring
a different approach.
One of the simplest definitions of
architecture is that it exists to enable
change. Architects aren't
employed just to draw diagrams.
They're employed to help organisations
make good decisions about change,
like introducing new capabilities,
reducing risk, balancing trade-offs,
managing tech debt,
improving resilience and
supporting business strategy.
Everything ultimately comes back to
understanding how today's architecture
can safely evolve into tomorrow's.
To do that requires
understanding the current state.
Unfortunately, that is
often the hardest part.
Architecture knowledge is
rarely found in one place.
Instead, it's scattered
across the organisation.
Some information lives in source
code or Infrastructure as Code,
some in ADRs, in Confluence, diagrams,
slide decks or monitoring systems.
Some still exists in the memories of
people that have moved on years ago.
Each source contains part of the truth.
None contains the whole picture.
Even worse, those sources
are continuously changing.
Documentation slowly becomes outdated.
Diagrams become disconnected from reality.
Projects introduce new technologies.
Teams change. Businesses evolve.
The architecture moves while our
understanding slowly falls behind.
This isn't the fault of architects.
It's simply the consequence of
architecture being a living system rather
than a static asset.
The industry already has excellent tools.
Confluence is good at documentation.
Git is excellent at versioning files.
Terraform manages infrastructure. Mermaid,
PlantUML and C4 are
excellent at doing diagrams.
Enterprise architecture management
platforms help organisations catalogue
systems and relationships. The problem
is not that these tools are poor.
The problem is that none of them
truly understand the architecture.
Each tool represents one
projection of reality.
A diagram is a view. An
ADR records a decision.
Source code records implementation.
Infrastructure describes a deployment.
Documentation explains concepts.
The architect is left connecting
those pieces together.
In other words, the architecture
exists largely in people's heads.
When architecture knowledge
becomes fragmented,
every architectural activity
becomes more difficult.
Understanding the current
state takes longer.
Designs duplicate existing capabilities
because nobody knows what already
exists. Architectural decisions
are forgotten and later repeated.
Impact analysis becomes
a manual investigation.
Documentation slowly loses relevance.
Architects spend more time
searching for information
than reasoning about solutions.
None of these problems are
individually catastrophic.
Collectively, they consume an
enormous amount of time and increase
uncertainty across every project.
So why now? Many of these
observations are not new.
I've been thinking about them for years.
The difference is that now I believe
we finally have technology capable of
helping. Large language models are
not only interesting because they can
generate code. They are interesting
because they can reason across large
collections of unstructured
information. They can identify patterns,
summarise documents, highlight
contradictions, ask follow-up questions,
extract structure, work
with incomplete evidence.
None of these capabilities
replace architectural thinking.
Instead, they augment it. That
changes the kind of tools we can
realistically build. For the first time,
it feels practical to imagine software
that helps architects understand
architecture rather than
simply documenting it.
So, the vision. Articulate began as a
side project to scratch my own itch.
Like many personal projects,
it started small. An idea here,
a prototype there, several
false starts, of course,
more discarded ideas than
successful ones. Over time,
those ideas converged into
a much broader question:
Can architecture become a continuously
evolving body of knowledge instead of
a collection of disconnected documents?
That single question sits
at the heart of Articulate.
It is not intended to replace architects,
nor is it intended to generate
documentation automatically.
Instead, it explores whether
AI can become
a genuine architectural collaborator,
helping architects to discover knowledge,
challenge assumptions,
understand the trade-offs,
maintain architectural
context, reason about change,
preserve the decisions and continuously
improve their understanding of
complex systems. Whether that proves
achievable remains to be seen.
That uncertainty is exactly
why this project exists.
One of the goals of this journal is
to avoid beginning with technology.
Before discussing services,
databases, frameworks and AI models,
I want to understand the
architectural principles
that should shape the system.
Questions such as:
What does it mean to version architecture?
Can confidence be modelled?
Should evidence become part
of the architectural model?
Can conversations become
the primary interface?
What role should AI
play in decision making?
Where should humans
remain firmly in control?
Answering these questions is more
important than selecting any particular
technology stack. Technology will change.
Principles should endure.
If Articulate succeeds,
I don't believe it will be because
it produces better diagrams or more
documentation. It will succeed if
it helps architects spend less time
searching for information and more
time solving meaningful problems.
If it helps preserve architectural
knowledge, if it reduces uncertainty,
if it encourages better
architectural conversations,
if it helps explain the
consequences of change
before those changes are implemented.
Most importantly,
if it demonstrates that AI can become
a thoughtful architectural collaborator
rather than simply another
code generation tool.
So, looking ahead,
this episode has intentionally
avoided discussing implementation.
The purpose was to establish the
motivation behind the project.
Future episodes will explore the
architectural principles, requirements,
constraints and experiments that
will shape Articulate as it evolves.
Some ideas will succeed. Some will fail.
Many will change along the way.
That is exactly what this journal
intends to document because, ultimately,
Articulate is not about building software.
It's an exploration into how we
might build better architecture.